<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gaming | TimRayburn.net]]></title>
  <link href="http://TimRayburn.net/blog/categories/gaming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://TimRayburn.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-01T14:02:29-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://TimRayburn.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tim Rayburn]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fourth Friday Family Game Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://TimRayburn.net/blog/fourth-friday-family-game-night/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-21T15:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://TimRayburn.net/blog/fourth-friday-family-game-night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You are officially invited to join the consultants of Improving Enterprises for board games, fun and frivolity.  Every 4th Friday of the month we will gather for a family friendly night of games.  We'll have drinks of all sorts available, and a large selection of games.</p>

<h2>Who is invited?</h2>

<p>Everyone, regardless of age or skill.  Bring yourself, your kids, we've got games for all ages.  <strong>We ask that you sign up, if possible</strong>, in advance just to give us an idea of how many people are coming.  <a href="http://fffgn.eventbrite.com">Our registration site is located at this link.</a></p>

<h2>When is it?</h2>

<p>The Fourth Friday of every month, hence the name.  We'll officially start at 6:00pm, and run until ... well we'll play alot of games.  Leave when you'd like.</p>

<h2>Where is it?</h2>

<p>We're hosted at <a href="http://improvingenterprises.com">Improving Enterprises</a>, a fantastic company in the North Dallas area.  Their offices are at:</p>

<p><a href="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=16633+Dallas+Parkway+Suite+100+Addison,+TX+75001&amp;hl=en&amp;sll=31.168934,-100.076842&amp;sspn=18.524051,54.118652&amp;t=h&amp;hnear=16633+Dallas+Pkwy+%23100,+Addison,+Dallas,+Texas+75001&amp;z=17">16633 Dallas Parkway
Suite 100
Addison, TX 75001</a></p>

<h2>What games will you be playing?</h2>

<p>Pretty much everything.  If you're idea of a board game is the traditional American board games of Monopoly or Risk, then we've got you covered.</p>

<p>On the other hand, if you're a fan of Euro-style board games, then we've got people who would love to play a game of Dominion, Settlers of Catan, Small World, Agricola, or anything else you'd like to bring.</p>

<p>Are you an huge name on <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/">Board Game Geek</a>?  Bring your favorite game and teach us how to play!</p>

<h2>I don't know any of those games!</h2>

<p>Great!  We love to teach people how to play.</p>

<h2>I've got questions still...</h2>

<p>Contact one of our official Hosts, they'll be more than happy to field any questions you might have:</p>

<p><a href="http://TimRayburn.net">Tim Rayburn</a> can be reached at tim@timrayburn.net or 817-760-0002</p>

<p><a href="http://tycrockett.com">Ty Crockett</a> can be reached at ty.crockett@improvingenterprises.com</p>

<h2>Sponsors</h2>

<p>This event is graciously hosted by the incredible folks at <a href="http://improvingenterprises.com">Improving Enterprises</a>.  They open their offices, soda fridge, and other facilities to us on a monthly basis and we're thrilled to have their support.  If you're an IT professional, please chat with on of their employees who attend to learn more about this great company.</p>

<p><img src="http://timrayburn.net/images/ie-logo-small.jpg" alt="Improving Enterprises Logo" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
